Finding Aid for Jay Handler Schmidt papers, 1918-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jay Handler Schmidt papers 1918-1968
Schmidt, Jay Handler, 1891-
0.4 linear feet
852222 Aa 2
Alumnus of University of Michigan, and secretary of the University of Michigan Club of Suburban New Jersey. Correspondence and other materials relating to his alumni activities and his continuing interest in University affairs; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Jay Schmidt (donor no. 2139 ) and came to the library mainly in 1971 and 1974.
The collection is open to research.
Jay H. Schmidt graduated from the University of Michigan School of Engineering in 1916, with a degree in chemical engineering. He served in France during World War I, and did graduate work at the University of Montpellier (France) as a member of the Army School Detachment. In 1925, Schmidt founded Special Toiletries Corp., a contract cosmetics firm. He was president of the firm until his retirement in 1948.
Schmidt was a very loyal alumnus of the University of Michigan. He was a member of the University of Michigan Club of New York Scholarship Committee, an officer of the First District Alumni Association, and organizer and officer of the University of Michigan Club of Suburban New Jersey.
The Schmidt collection consists of 0.4 feet of papers covering the years 1918-1968, though concentrating in the period since 1944. There is a small folder of materials detailing his World War I service and a few letters concerning his interest in perfumes and fragrances. The collection also contains two folders and several letters relating to Schmidt's work as board member and fund-raiser on behalf of the University of Michigan Committee, Thomas E. Dewey for President, during the 1944 and 1948 elections. Much of the collection concerns other alumni activities, including a sample of letters relating to recruiting prospective students for the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Presidents--United States--Election--1944.; Presidents--United States--Election--1948.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1953.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Alumni Association.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; France.; Germany.; Military bands.; Military parades and ceremonies.; Victory celebrations--France.; World War, 1914-1918.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal and political
  - Correspondence, 1943-1968, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - World War I miscellanea (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Committee, Thomas E. Dewey for President
    - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Bills, disbursements, and other financial papers, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence concerning the possibility of organizing U-M Alumni to support Dewey for president in 1948, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Alumni Activities
  - Alumni Association of the University of Michigan, First District, 1944-1962, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Club of New York, Scholarship Committee
    - Agendas and minutes, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
    - Letters (sample) typical of his activities in recruiting prospective students for the U-M, 1949 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Club of Suburban New Jersey
    - Minutes and treasurer's statements, 1948-1963 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Association of the University of Michigan
    - Minutes, 1959-1962 of Student Governors Conference (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Alumni Clubs Council
    - Papers, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of various University of Michigan Clubs in New York and New Jersey, 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Association of the University of Michigan, Field Secretary's Bulletin, 1947-1961 (Box 1)
  - Michigan New Jersey News, published by University of Michigan Club of Suburban New Jersey, 1963 (Box 1)
  - College of Engineering of the University of Michigan. A survey of fund raising resources and a plan of campaign (Box 1)
    (mimeographed booklet prepared by Kersting, Brown and Co. 1948)
- Other materials
  - Correspondence concerning a projected article about residents of Putney, Vermont, who moved to the Western Reserve, Ohio, 1955-1959 (Box 1)
    (includes map of Putney showing location of cellar holes)
  - Miscellanea (drafts of letters and letters of editors) (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - University of Michigan and Thomas Dewey (Box 1)
  - World War I
    - French countryside and cities (Box 1)
    - Military activities and the Front (Box 1)
    - Victory celebrations (Box 1)